<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A meditacion vpon the Lordes prayer, made by Thomas Leuer, at Sayncte Mary Wol Churche in London. Anno. M.D.LI.</title>
            <author>Lever, Thomas, 1521-1577.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842204</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05392)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 660:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A meditacion vpon the Lordes prayer, made by Thomas Leuer, at Sayncte Mary Wol Churche in London. Anno. M.D.LI.</title>
                  <author>Lever, Thomas, 1521-1577.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Jhon Daye, dwelling ouer Aldersgate beneth Sainte Martins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1551]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A(-A8).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6838:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:6838:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditacion vpon the Lordes Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, made by Thomas <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euer, at Sayncte Mary-Wol chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
            <p>Anno. M.D.Li.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6838:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:6838:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
            <head>To the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reader.</head>
            <p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ropter, laborem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et gemitum pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perum, nunc exurga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dicit dominus.</q>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. xii.</note> Sure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye euen nowe in great ſcarſitie lack and dearth of meate, dryncke, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and all other neceſſaries, the ſorowful ſighes of the poore and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, muſte either ſinke into the riche mennes hartes, and from theim pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure relyue, and comforte, vnto the nedye members of Chriſtes bodye: or els directlye aſcende vnto the throne of Goddes Iuſtice, and from thence bryng downe indignacyon and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce, to deſtroye wycked worlde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, which being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfs in welth and aboundaunce, fele no gryete of their brothers diſtreſſe and miſery.</p>
            <p>¶But if any man, euery weke wil be content, to ſpare one meale of him ſelf, &amp; beſtowe the price of that meale in Charitable Almoſe to relyue the pore, and the time of the ſame in god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly meditacion and Praier, to diſpoſe his owne mynde deuoutly: then ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:6838:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
al ſuche feele and taſte, both of poore mennes honger, and of Godly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and praier, yea, and many poore be much relyued, and no rich man any thynge charged, and ſo thereby Goddes vengaunce auoided and Gods grace procured, when as faſtyng and praier doeth plucke out of mennes hartes coueteouſnes which is the roote of all euil and the cauſe of all calamities that nowe dooe trouble, greue, and daunger al men: This meditacion therfore of the Lordes praier, ſhall be good comfortable ſpirituall fode, in that tyme of bodi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly abſtinence.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>typographic decoration</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6838:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>☞A medytacyon vpon the Lordes praier.</head>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vre father whyche arte in heauen.</label>
We (gloriouſly formed vnto the Image of thy deuyne Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye, created by the gracyous goodnes vnto higheſt honor, howbeit, by our owne ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes diſfigured wyth vilenes deſeruinge dampnacion, and yet by Chriſtes death reſtored vnto grace, to be citeze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wyth ſaynctes of the family of God) nowe all together in Chriſten vnite, as members of one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, wyth thys one voyce, for the manifolde miſeries of eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry member, and worthy meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:6838:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
of Chriſt our heade, praye, deſire, and truſte, to obtaine of the our heauenly father, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng vnto thy gracious good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, mighty power, and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promes, vnto vs that aſke aboundaunce of thy grace.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> That thy name maie bee halowed.</label> That thy dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power and glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſty, may be certainly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; reuerently honored. That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hartes of vs men, by thy word and praier, maie be ſanctified fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worldly vanyties &amp; fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſtes, ſo that wee wyth all that we haue, ſeruynge the in holines &amp; righteouſnes, maye ſhine ſo afore menne vpon the earthe, that they thereby maye be occaſyoned, to honour, and
<pb facs="tcp:6838:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
glorify the, our father in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Thy kingdome come <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/>
               </label> Thy word be ſo frutefully Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched vnto vs thy people, that we may be throughly inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and taught, to bridle oure ſenſuall appetyte by naturall reaſon, and ſubmit our wyttie reaſon vnto a Godlye ſpirite, and try our ſpirits by the true Scryptures, ſo that within vs may reygne the Kyngdome of God, whiche is neither meate nor dryncke, but righteouſnes, peace, and comfort in the holy Ghoſte, by the which we nowe taſtyng of thy heauenly ioyes, may be made from henceforth wery of all worldly vanytyes, continually wiſhyng and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng for the ſpedy apperance
<pb facs="tcp:6838:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
and commynge of thy eternal and euerlaſtynge kyngdome.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> ¶Thy wil be done in earth as it is in heauen.</label> In heauen the Angelles of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerent loue, dooe thy wyll and commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wyth comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table courage, and ioyful ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: in hell the wicked ſpirits through malyce and enuie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinyng and grudging, do tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vexe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes, what ſoeuer they be doing: and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth we men beynge ſubiecte vnto ſyn do thynke it a labor &amp; paine, to be occupied in any thing that is good and godly. Wherefore we praye that the grace of thy heauenly Spirit may ſo worcke in our earthlye bodies, that our mindes maie
<pb facs="tcp:6838:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
be delyuered from ſynne and vanity, frely to delite and take pleſure in Godlines and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſo that we with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courage, maye fynd delite and pleaſure to dooe thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement and wil, beynge men vpon earth, as the glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous company of Angelles do which be in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <label>¶Geue vs this day our <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iiii."/> daily bread.</label> We beynge in great nede, and not able of our ſelfes to deſerue any thing be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeche thy Fatherlye goodnes of thy bounteous liberalite, to geue frely vnto vs al in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, ſo that none be hurte or hyndered ſeuerally, this daye when as we crie, conſtrained by preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nede, not craftely cra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng
<pb facs="tcp:6838:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
for vayn care againſt to morowe, our dayly bread, oure daily and neceſſary foode and relyue, both bodily and goſtly and eſpecyally the Spiritual fode of Chriſtes fleſh and his bloude, by dayly Prechyng of the Goſpell, and miniſtracion of the Sacramentes, to reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe, refreſhe, and renue oure hartes &amp; mindes, with the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortable reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes death and his paſſion dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be vſed for neceſſary and ſpiritual conſolacion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="v."/> Forgeue vs our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, as wee forgeue theym that treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte vs.</label> Geue vnto vs that felyng and knowyng our owne ſynfulnes, doo nede and
<pb facs="tcp:6838:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
deſire thy mercyfull forgeue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of oure treſpaces and fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whych we haue committed againſt thy deuine Maieſty, ſo that we frely forgeuinge other that haue offended vs in anye thyng whatſoeuer it be, maye be ſure that mercy ſpryngynge in the, hath proceded vnto vs beyng graciouſly offred of the hath bene thankfully receiued of vs, and being charitably v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of vs towardes other ſhal moſt certaynlye be confirmed and enlarged of the towardes vs, and ſo finally, by gracious mercye ſpringinge and proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng from the, all fautes and treſpaſſes ſhalbe freely forge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, euen as thoſe which other haue committed agaynſte vs, ſo likewiſe thoſe that we haue
<pb facs="tcp:6838:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
done agaynſte the.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vi."/> And leade vs not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptacion.</label> And ſuffer not the deuil, by thabule of thy benefytes, to leade vs captiue into deceytefull and dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, drawing vs by deinteth meates vnto gredye glottony, by money and riches vnto vnſaciable couetouſnes. and by welth and proſperytye vnto pryde and vayneglorye, and by all thy godlye gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous giftes, vnto euerye dyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe abhomynable ſynne.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vii."/> ¶But delyuer vs from all euyll.</label> Deliuer our good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abuſe, oure bodyes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corrupcion, our Soules from dampnacion, yea, deliuer vs by Chriſte, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bondage of
<pb facs="tcp:6838:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
ſynne, vnto the libertye of the Goſpel, ſo that without daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of dyuelyſhe temptacion driuyng vnto euerlaſtyng da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion we maye ſerue thee in holines and righteouſneſſe al the dayes of oure lyues, wyth moſt certain and comfortable hope, of euerlaſtynge life and ſaluacion, through Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu in whom our hope and thy promes is moſte certain, that is to ſay. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. SOBEIT.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6838:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
            <p>Imprinted at London by Ihon Daye, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ouer Alderſgate beneth Sainte Martins.</p>
            <p>¶Theſe bookes are to bee ſolde at hys ſhop in Schepeſyde, by the Litle Counduit at the ſygne of the Reſurreccion.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>typographic decoration</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum. Per ſepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nium.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6838:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
